Guide to the Othniel Charles Marsh Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Marsh family, 1817-1900; Series II
  - Family Correspondence
    - Caleb Robert Marsh
      - Marsh, George E., 1856 (Box 38, Folder 56)
    - John Marsh, Sr.
      - Abbott, Benjamin, 1825 (Box 38, Folder 57)
      - Marsh, Samuel, 1857 (Box 38, Folder 58)
    - John Marsh, Jr.
      - Waters, William, 1850 (Box 38, Folder 59)
    - Mary Marsh
      - Waters, Mary Peabody Marsh, 1844-1845 (Box 39, Folder 60)
    - Mary Gaines Peabody Marsh
      - Allen, Samuel R., 1832 (Box 39, Folder 61)
      - Barker, E., 1825 (Box 39, Folder 62)
      - Brown, Fanny F.M., 1831 (Box 39, Folder 63)
      - Cook, Hannah S., 1831 (Box 39, Folder 64)
      - Daniels, Judith D.P. Russell, 1823-1834 (Box 39, Folder 65)
      - Dodge, Mary, 1828 (Box 39, Folder 66)
      - Emerson, Eunice, 1828 (Box 39, Folder 67)
      - Emerson, Hannah, 1822 (Box 39, Folder 68)
      - George, Elizabeth Mary, 1820 (Box 39, Folder 69)
      - Kimball, Eliphalet, 1825 (Box 39, Folder 70)
      - Little, Elbridge, 1834 (Box 39, Folder 71)
      - Marsh, Fanny F.
        See: Brown, Fanny F. Marsh
      - Little, Sophronfa P. Peabody, 1825-1831 (Box 39, Folder 72)
      - Marsh, Mary, 1826-1834 (Box 39, Folder 73)
      - Nichols, Roxann, 1823 (Box 39, Folder 74)
      - Parsons, Emily S., 1824 (Box 39, Folder 75)
      - Paysons, Louisa S., 1824 (Box 39, Folder 76)
      - Peabody, David, 1827-1831 (Box 39, Folder 77)
      - Peabody, George, 1822-1834 (Box 39, Folder 78)
      - Peabody, George (son of David), 1831 (Box 39, Folder 79)
      - Peabody, Jeremiah D., 1822-1834 (Box 39, Folder 80)
      - Peabody, Judith Dodge
        See: Daniels, Judith Dodge Peabody Russell
      - Peabody, Thomas, 1824-1834 (Box 39, Folder 81)
      - Peabody, Tom and Judith, 1829 (Box 39, Folder 82)
      - Russell, Jeremiah, 1834 (Box 39, Folder 83)
      - Russell, Judith Dodge Peabody
        See: Daniels, Judith D. P. Russell
      - Spofford, Apphia, 1822 (Box 39, Folder 84)
      - Webster, Lyrena, 1834 (Box 39, Folder 85)
    - Mary Lattin Marsh
      - Darrow, Sarah, 1836 (Box 39, Folder 86)
      - Lattin, Wright, 1837 (Box 39, Folder 87)
      - Marsh, Mary, 1845 (Box 39, Folder 88)
      - Waters, Mary Peabody Marsh, 1848-1850 (Box 39, Folder 89)
    - Mary Peabody Marsh
      See: Waters, Mary P.M
    - Othniel Charles Marsh
      - Brown, Fanny, 1881 (Box 40, Folder 90)
      - Brown, John H., 1856 (Box 40, Folder 91)
      - Brown, Minta, 1857-1860 (Box 40, Folder 92)
      - Brown, Samuel, 1856-1862 (Box 40, Folder 93)
      - Cameron, Alice F., 1881-1886 (Box 40, Folder 94)
      - Campbell, Sarah Adelaide, 1869 (Box 40, Folder 95)
      - Caverno, D.H., 1860 (Box 40, Folder 96)
      - Chandler, Charles W., 1865-1867 (Box 40, Folder 97)
      - Chandler, Julia Peabody, 1860-1887 (Box 40, Folder 98)
      - Chandler, Mary Humphrey
        See: Lewis, Mary H.C.
      - Cogswell, Elizabeth Lord
        See: Dixon, Elizabeth Lord C.
      - Daniels, Judith D.P. Russell, 1855-1856 (Box 40, Folder 99)
      - Daniels, Judith D.P. Russell, 1857-1858 (Box 40, Folder 100)
      - Daniels, Judith D.P. Russell, 1859-1861 (Box 40, Folder 101)
      - Daniels, Judith D.P. Russell, 1862-1865 (Box 40, Folder 102)
      - Daniels, Judith D.P. Russell, 1866-1869 (Box 40, Folder 103)
      - Dixon, Eliza
        See: Marsh, Eliza Dixon
      - Dixon, Elizabeth Lord Cogswell, 1858-1860 (Box 40, Folder 104)
      - Dixon, Elizabeth Lord Cogswell, 1861-1862 (Box 40, Folder 105)
      - Dixon, Elizabeth Lord Cogswell, 1863-1867 (Box 40, Folder 106)
      - Dixon, James (1814-1873), 1858-1867 (Box 40, Folder 107)
      - Endicott, William C. (1826-1900), 1887 (Box 40, Folder 108)
      - Frost, Charles L., 1876 (Box 40, Folder 109)
      - Hawkins, J.W., 1866 (Box 40, Folder 110)
      - Howland, Florence K., undated (Box 40, Folder 111)
      - Iris Journal, Editor, 1851-1854 (Box 40, Folder 112)
      - Lewis, Mary H. Chandler, 1884-1887 (Box 40, Folder 113)
      - Little, Sophronia Peabody, 1856-1857 (Box 40, Folder 114)
      - McChesney, W.H., 1862 (Box 40, Folder 115)
      - Marsh, Caleb R., 1856-1860 (Box 40, Folder 116)
      - Marsh, Caleb R., 1861-1867 (Box 40, Folder 117)
      - Marsh, Eliza Dixon, 1858-1861 April (Box 41, Folder 118)
      - Marsh, Eliza Dixon, 1861 May-1872 (Box 41, Folder 119)
      - Marsh, Elizabeth Loring
        See: Shoulters, Elizabeth Marsh
      - Marsh, Elizabeth Taylor, 1858 (Box 41, Folder 120)
      - Marsh, Fannie [B], 1880 (Box 41, Folder 121)
      - Marsh, Fannie D. [Mrs. James P.], 1879-1891 (Box 41, Folder 122)
      - Marsh, George E., 1882 (Box 41, Folder 123)
      - Marsh, Hannah F., 1881-1884 (Box 41, Folder 124)
      - Marsh, James Sr., 1860-1866 (Box 41, Folder 125)
      - Marsh, James P., 1858-1866 (Box 41, Folder 126)
      - Marsh, James P., 1869-1899 (Box 41, Folder 127)
      - Marsh, Lucius R., 1888 (Box 41, Folder 128)
      - Marsh, Martha Lattin
        See: Martha L.M. Walker
      - Marsh, Mary, 1856-1864 (Box 41, Folder 129)
      - Marsh, Mary Lattin, 1857-1861 (Box 41, Folder 130)
      - Marsh, Mary Waters
        See: Williamson, Mary W.M.
      - Mason, Ellen, 1880-1887 (Box 41, Folder 131)
      - Munson, Mary Peabody, 1878 (Box 41, Folder 132)
      - Outhwaite, Ellen Peabody, 1881 (Box 41, Folder 133)
      - Peabody, Arthur J., 1866-1898 (Box 41, Folder 134)
      - Peabody, Charles R., 1867 (Box 41, Folder 135)
      - Peabody, Ella E. Russell, 1872 (Box 41, Folder 136)
      - Peabody, Ellen R., 1865 (Box 41, Folder 137)
      - Peabody, Ellen S.
        See: Outhwaite, Ellen S.P.
      - Peabody, Georqe, 1856-1864 (Box 41, Folder 138)
      - Peabody, George, 1865-1869 (Box 41, Folder 139)
      - Peabody, George H., 1853-1882 (Box 41, Folder 140)
      - Peabody, James Russell, 1881-1883 (Box 41, Folder 141)
      - Peabody, Judith Dodge
      - Peabody, Julia
        See: Chandler, Julia Peabody
      - Peabody, Robert S., 1856-1891 (Box 41, Folder 142)
      - Peabody, Sophronia
        See: Little, Sophronia Peabody
      - Russell, Ella E.
        See: Peabody, Ella E.R.
      - Russell, George P., 1856-1876 (Box 42, Folder 143)
      - Russell, Jeremiah, 1867 (Box 42, Folder 144)
      - Russell, Judith D. Peabody
      - Russell, Lucy C., 1870-1876 (Box 42, Folder 145)
      - Sanders, Mary A., 1853 (Box 42, Folder 146)
      - Shoulters, Elizabeth L. Marsh, 1856-1894 (Box 42, Folder 147)
      - Shoulters, Harvey J., 1875-1896 (Box 42, Folder 148)
      - Shoulters, Mabel, 1899 (Box 42, Folder 149)
      - Walker, Edward C., 1862-1869 March (Box 42, Folder 150)
      - Walker, Edward C., 1869 April-1890 (Box 42, Folder 151)
      - Walker, Martha L. Marsh, 1855-1856 (Box 42, Folder 152)
      - Walker, Martha L. Marsh, 1857 (Box 42, Folder 153)
      - Walker, Martha L. Marsh, 1858 (Box 42, Folder 154)
      - Walker, Martha L. Marsh, 1859-1860 (Box 42, Folder 155)
      - Walker, Martha L. Marsh, 1861-1897 (Box 42, Folder 156)
      - Waters, Robert H., Sr., 1861 (Box 42, Folder 157)
      - Waters, Robert H., Jr., 1868-1879 (Box 42, Folder 158)
      - Whitney, Helen C., undated (Box 42, Folder 159)
      - Williamson, Mary W. Marsh, 1869-1881 (Box 42, Folder 160)
      - Williamson, Sam E., 1877-1885 (Box 42, Folder 161)
    - Jeremiah David Peabody
      - Little, Sophronia P., 1830 (Box 42, Folder 162)
    - Judith Dodge Peabody
      - Peabody, David, 1825 (Box 42, Folder 163)
      - Peabody, George, 1830 (Box 42, Folder 164)
    - Mary Peabody Marsh Waters
      - Marsh, Hannah F., 1841-1844 (Box 42, Folder 165)
      - Walker, Martha L. M., 1850 (Box 42, Folder 166)
  - Special Files
    - Caleb Marsh
      - Appointment as sergeant to army, 1821 (Box 43, Folder 167)
      - Benediction, undated (Box 43, Folder 168)
      - Bond of $2000 to Othniel C. Marsh with receipt of payment of that bond, 1854-1858 (Box 43, Folder 169)
      - Calling Cards, undated (Box 43, Folder 170)
      - Church Memberships, 1834-1845 (Box 43, Folder 171)
      - Deed of Trust. Property held for O.C. Marsh and Mary P. Marsh, 1837 (Box 43, Folder 172)
      - Expenses of Mary P. Marsh, [1846-1847] (Box 43, Folder 173)
      - Inventories (furniture and real estate), 1834-1846 (Box 43, Folder 174)
      - Lease of Property to O.C. Marsh. Agreement never put into effect, 1860 (Box 43, Folder 175)
      - Mortgage of property to O.C. Marsh, 1854-1858 (Box 43, Folder 176)
      - Notebook, 1819 (Box 43, Folder 177)
      - Notes on property and death dates of relatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 178)
      - Obituary showing death of his son George Peabody, 1835 (Box 43, Folder 179)
      - Promissory notes, 1829-1839 (Box 43, Folder 180)
      - Property deeds, 1836 (Box 43, Folder 181)
      - Recommendation of his integrity, 1840 (Box 43, Folder 182)
      - Teaching Certificates, 1819-1826 (Box 43, Folder 183)
    - John Marsh Sr.
      - Deed of Trust. Appointing James Marsh as Trustee, 1846 (Box 43, Folder 184)
      - Property Deeds, 1817-1846 (Box 43, Folder 185)
      - Settlement of Estate, 1846-1861 (Box 43, Folder 186)
    - Mary Gaines Peabody Marsh
      - Compositions, 1823-1824 (Box 43, Folder 187)
      - Copybooks, 1821 (Box 43, Folder 188)
      - Momentos, 1813-1834 (Box 43, Folder 189)
      - Scrapbook I, 1822 (Box 43, Folder 190)
      - Scrapbook II, 1825-1834 (Box 43, Folder 191)
      - Silhouettes, 1824 (Box 43, Folder 192)
    - Othniel Charles Marsh
      - American Association for Advancement of Science (minutes of Proceedings annotated by O.C. Marsh), 1878 (Box 43A, Folder 193)
      - Appointment as delegate to Zoology Congress, 1898 (Box 43A, Folder 194)
      - Autographs, undated (Box 43A, Folder 195)
      - Death - Announcement by Yale, 1899 (Box 43A, Folder 196)
      - Form Letter regarding display of his specimens at other institutions, undated (Box 43A, Folder 197)
      - A. Holmes, Attorney. Correspondence regarding sale of property owned by Marsh Family, 1866-1868 (Box 43A, Folder 198)
      - Insurance Coverage. Record of coverage on property, 1889-1898 (Box 43A, Folder 199)
      - Insurance Coverage (Fire). Notification of expiration date on farm building, 1866 (Box 43A, Folder 200)
      - Inventory of household possessions, 1884 (Box 43A, Folder 201)
      - Memorial Church and Society. Thank you note for O.C. Marsh's gift to Church, 1869 (Box 43A, Folder 202)
      - Minority. Documents pertaining to property held in trust for him, 1842-1852 (Box 43A, Folder 203)
      - Momentos, 1856-1895 (Box 43A, Folder 204)
      - Portraits of George Peabody (receipt for and correspondence about.), 1876 (Box 43A, Folder 205)
      - Property assessment form and assessed valuation of property on 360 Prospect, 1894 (Box 43A, Folder 206)
      - Purchase of Real Estate at Auction. Newsclipping, [1889] (Box 43A, Folder 207)
      - Receipts, Miscellaneous, 1865-1875 (Box 43A, Folder 208)
      - Settlement of Estate. Catalogues: Sale of Rare and Beautiful Orchids (two copies, not filmed); Collection of the late Professor O.C. Marsh (two copies--the copy with F.B. Dexter's annotations was not filmed; the Bostwick copy was filmed); Microfilm reel of Thomas Kirby's auction catalogue, 1899-1900 (Box 43A, Folder 209)
      - Settlement of Estate. Protest (by R.H. Waters, Jr.) of will, 1899 (Box 43A, Folder 210)
      - Last Will and Testament of O.C. Marsh (not filmed), 1898 (Box 43A, Folder 210A)
      - Correspondence to O.C. Marsh by unknown author regarding settlement of estate of Mrs. Peabody, 1899 (Box 43A, Folder 211)
      - Social Invitations, undated (Box 43A, Folder 212)
      - Verses by O.C. Marsh, 1881-1895 (Box 43A, Folder 213)
      - Verse to OCM by Clarence King, 1877 (Box 43A, Folder 214)
    - George Peabody
      - Address to Danvers, Mass. school children (newsclipping), 1866 (Box 43A, Folder 215)
      - Benevolent Deeds, 1864-1868 (Box 43A, Folder 216)
      - Death: Obituaries and Resumes of his life and accomplishments (newsclippings), 1869-1870 (Box 43A, Folder 217)
      - Editorial and Four News Reports in His Honor, 1866 (Box 43A, Folder 218)
      - Miscellaneous letters asking for donations, 1866-1867 (Box 43A, Folder 219)
      - News Journal of travels through Prussia, undated (Box 43A, Folder 220)
      - Newspaper clippings recording comments on civil war, 1861 (Box 43A, Folder 221)
    - Mary Peabody Marsh Waters
      - Biblical quotations and list of expenditures, 1838 (Box 43A, Folder 222)
      - Receipt for school expenses, 1866 (Box 43A, Folder 223)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Attachment writ against C.H. Daniels, Court Summons of several plaintiffs including O.C. Marsh, 1861 (Box 43B, Folder 224)
      - Expedition. Black Hills Expedition to new gold fields. Negative and copy of poster., 1875 (Box 43B, Folder 225)
      - Negatives of 2 pictures and maps of 3 proposed trips, 1875 (Box 43B, Folder 225A)
      - Expedition. Glaciers of Western U.S. (Newspaper report), undated (Box 43B, Folder 226)
      - Expedition. Mt. Hood Ascent. Diary by George Davidson; newspaper report, 1870 (Box 43B, Folder 227)
      - Expedition. Yukon River Exploration. Headed by Lt. Schwatka (a newspaper report), 1884 (Box 43B, Folder 228)
      - Greeting Cards, undated (Box 43B, Folder 229)
      - Meeting. Troy Scientific Meeting (a newspaper report), 1870 (Box 43B, Folder 230)
      - Newspaper clipping--miscellaneous. (Presumably sent to O.C. Marsh during his German sojourn), 1864 (Box 43B, Folder 231)
      - Newspaper clippings about specimens (Lizard, Giants of Arkansas, Bones of Elk, Sea Serpents, Prehistoric remains of Indian mounds), 1875 (Box 43B, Folder 232)
      - Photo. James Dixon, Jr., [1860] (Box 43B, Folder 233)
      - Photos. Friends of O.C. Marsh from his album, 1860-1863 (Box 43B, Folder 234)
      - Photo. House in Danvers, Mass., undated (Box 43B, Folder 235)
      - Photos. Peabody Family, 1860 (Box 43B, Folder 236)
      - Photos. Unidentified Fossil Specimens, undated (Box 43B, Folder 237)
      - Photos. Unidentified portraits from O.C. Marsh's album, undated (Box 43B, Folder 238)
      - Photos. Yale scientists and their families (from O.C. Marsh's album), undated (Box 43B, Folder 239)
      - Program. Dedication of Memorial Church, 1868 (Box 43B, Folder 240)
      - Program. Historical lecture series by Rev. John Lord, undated, October 11-November 11 (Box 43B, Folder 241)
      - Receipt. Barnum, Henry. For subscription to Silliman's Journal, 1870 (Box 43B, Folder 242)
      - Regulations, Yale College, undated (Box 43B, Folder 243)
      - Religious Material. Chronological Table of Time collected from the Bible, [1878] (Box 43B, Folder 244)
      - Settlement of Estate of Marsh Clan, 1854 (Box 43B, Folder 245)
      - Trust Deed. Lucy A. Stevens to Northern Trust Co., undated (Box 43B, Folder 246)
      - Gegenbaur, Dr. Carl. Untersuchungen Vergleichenden Anatomie der Wirbelthiere, volumes 1and 2 (not filmed), 1864-1865 (Box 43B, Folder 247)
      - Skeleton sketches (Box 56)
- Education of O. C. Marsh, 1827-1897; Series III
  Materials documenting Marsh's education include early school catalogues, receipts, prayer books, autographs, and his Yale notebooks on chemistry, geology, and meteorology. The series also contains his Berlin notes on zoology and paleontology and his Breslau notes on echinoderms and geognosie, song books from Yale and Heidelberg, and his passport, letter of credit, and German diplomas.
  - Early Schools, 1827-1843 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Testament and Psalms: Prayer Rook, 1854, undated (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Philips Academy (Andover). Receipts and clipping, 1854-1856 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Phillips Academy (Andover). Marsh Collection of Autographs, 1856 July (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Phillips Academy (Andover). Marsh Collection of Autographs, 1857 July (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Yale Autograph Book, 1860 September (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Andover Building Photos, 1856 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Andover Faculty Photos, 1856 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Andover Student Photos, 1856 (Box 45, Folder 9 - 10)
  - Photos of Yale Classmates, 1860 (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - Photos. Duplicates of W. Park, undated (Box 45, Folder 12)
  - Yale Expenses (Miscellaneous), 1856-1860 (Box 46, Folder 13)
  - Yale Lectures, 1857-1859 (Box 46, Folder 14)
  - Yale Notes on Chemistry, 1859 (Box 46, Folder 15)
  - Yale Notes on Geology and Meteorology, 1860 (Box 46, Folder 16)
  - Heidelberg and Berlin notes, 1863 (Box 46, Folder 17)
  - Berlin Zoology Notebooks, 1863-1864 (Box 46, Folder 18)
  - Berlin Zoology Notes, 1864 (Box 46, Folder 19)
  - Berlin notes on Paleontology, 1863-1864 (Box 46, Folder 20)
  - Berlin notes on Paleontology and Ehrenberg, 1864 (Box 46, Folder 21)
  - Berlin Notes on Geognosie, 1864 (Box 46, Folder 22)
  - Breslau Notes on Echinoderms and Geognosie, 1864 (Box 47, Folder 23)
  - Breslau Notes on Geognosie, 1865 (Box 47, Folder 24)
  - Marsh's Passports, 1862, 1897 (Box 47, Folder 25)
  - Marsh's list of Correspondents, Letter of Credit, 1863 (Box 47, Folder 26)
  - German Mementos of 0. C. Marsh, 1863-1865 (Box 47, Folder 27)
  - Yale and Heidelberg Songs, 1858-1863 (Box 47, Folder 28)
  - Degrees, Honorary Degrees, and Membership Certificates.[for listing of contents of this Folio, see Appendix] (Box 47A, Folder 29)
- Writings of O. C. Marsh, 1847-1860; Series IV
  Marsh's writings include unpublished materials, such as diaries, notebooks, and compositions written at Andover and Yale.
  - Diary and Notebooks, 1851-1854; cuid1599 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Andover Journal, 1854-1857; cuid1600 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Compositions
    - 1847, cuid1601 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - 1848, cuid1602 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - 1849, cuid1603 (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - 1850, cuid1604 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - 1852, cuid1605 (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - 1853, cuid1606 (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - 1854, cuid1607 (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - 1855, cuid1608 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - 1856, cuid1609 (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - 1857, cuid1610 (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - 1858, cuid1611 (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - 1859, cuid1612 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - 1860, cuid1613 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - "C" Compositions, undated; cuid1614 (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - "E" and "F" Compositions, undated; cuid1615 (Box 48, Folder 17)
    - "H" and "I" Compositions, undated; cuid1616 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - "L" Compositions, undated; cuid1617 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - "M" Compositions, undated; cuid1618 (Box 48, Folder 20)
    - "N" Compositions, undated; cuid1619 (Box 48, Folder 21)
    - "P" Compositions, undated; cuid1620 (Box 48, Folder 22)
    - "R", "S", and "T" Compositions, undated; cuid1621 (Box 48, Folder 23)
    - "U", "V" and "W" Compositions, Undated; cuid1622 (Box 48, Folder 24)
  - "The Mirror," Andover
    - 1855 July, cuid1623 (Box 48, Folder 25)
    - 1855 November, cuid1624 (Box 48, Folder 26)
    - 1856 March, cuid1625 (Box 48, Folder 27)
- Biographical material, 1828-1898; Series V
  The biographical material in this series includes five chapters of Marsh's projected autobiography, begun the year before his death and known as his "Narrative Volume." One chapter of this unfinished work, condensed in the Schuchert-Le Vene biography, provides a vivid account of a buffalo hunt when Marsh was caught on muleback in a stampeding herd. Also included are letters between Ernest Howe and George Bird Grinnell and between Howe and Schuchert concerning biographies of Marsh, a 1940 exchange between George F. Eaton and J. Donald Adams of the New York Times, and an album of obituary clippings on Marsh.
  - O. C. Marsh's Narrative Volume, Chapter I, Draft, 1898 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - O. C. Marsh's Narrative Volume, Chapter I, 1898 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - O. C. Marsh's Narrative Volume, Chapter I (carbon copy), 1898 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - O. C. Marsh's Kansas Stories, no's 1, 2, 3 and 11, 1898 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - O. C. Marsh's Kansas Stories, no's 1, 2, 3 and 11 (carbon copy), 1898 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re Howe-Grinnell Book on O. C. Marsh, 1928 January-November (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Grinnell's proposed Introduction to O. C. Marsh Narrative, 1929 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Grinnell's copy of Marsh's Narrative Volume, Chapter I and no's 1, 2, 3 and 11, 1929 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - J. W. Wadsworth's copy of Marsh's Narrative Volume, Chapter I and no's 1, 2, 3 and 11, 1929 (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - J. W. Wadsworth copy of Marsh Narrative, carbon copy: Chapter I, no's. 1, 2, 3, and 11, 1929 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Howe notes for Address on O. C. Marsh (1931) and Prudden's account of 1873 expedition (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Howe's notes for Marsh Biograph, 1929, 1931 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence re Howe-Grinnell book on Marsh, 1931 (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - Howe's book on Marsh, Introduction, 1932 (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - Howe's Book on Marsh, Chapters I, II, IV, 1932 (Box 49, Folder 15)
  - Schuchert-Howe letters on material for Marsh book, 1937-1938 (Box 49, Folder 16)
  - Pamphlet: "Some Old Houses and Historic Sites in Andover", 1932 (Box 49, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence re O. C. Marsh Biography (George F. Eaton, Donald Adams, and Bernhard Knollenberg correspondence), 1940 (Box 49, Folder 18)
  - Printed Matter from Lincoln Lore and New Haven Colony Historical Society, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 19)
  - Album of obituary clippings of O. C. Marsh (not filmed), 1899 (Box 49A)
- Cardiff Giant hoax, 1869-1938; Series VI
  Material relating to the Cardiff Giant Hoax of 1869, which kept recurring in the news until 1918. Marsh was always skeptical. He was asked in 1869 to authenticate the giant, and concluded that the alleged giant was no fossil, but a hand-carved sculpture that had been buried in Onondaga County, New York, so that it might be exhumed in an attempt to deceive the public.
  - Promotional pamphlets on Cardiff Giant (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Letter of O. C. Marsh re: Cardiff Giant (letter published in New York Herald\) (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Cardiff Giant newsclippings, 1897-1918 (Box 50, Folder 3 - 4)
  - References on Cardiff Giant for Marsh biography, 1938 (Box 50, Folder 5)
- Red Cloud Agency, 1838-1891; Series VII
  Materials documenting the Red Cloud Agency controversy, precipitated by Marsh after he had personally observed how the local agents of the Bureau of Indian Affairs issued short and shoddy rations to their charges. By calling attention to these corrupt practices, Marsh won the enmity of certain Washington bureaucrats and politicians. Marsh's crusade garnered strong editorial and public support, and Red Cloud visited New Haven to thank Marsh in person. Included in this series are the essential government reports and publications pertaining to the controversy, as well as correspondence (arranged chronologically) for the period from 1873-1876, plus a few items dated later. Among the many letters congratulating Marsh on his exposure of these scandals, Thaddeus H. Stanton wrote succinctly on June 19, 1875: "Go after the thieves, old boy, and make it hot for 'em." Additional references to the Red Cloud controversy can be found in Series I. General Correspondence, in folders for the following: Charles H. Denison, Ulysses S. Grant, Red Cloud, Thaddeus H. Stanton, and Wiliam Welsh.
  - O.C. Marsh statements re Red cloud, 1873 September-November (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Statements re issue of beef, 1873 December 6 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Red Cloud Report to Indian Commission by Samuel Walker, 1873 December 6 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Newsclippings and Red Cloud Contracts, 1874 Feb, July (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Report of Bevier on Contract between Saville and Appleton, 1874 October 21 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Report of J. D. Bevier on Visit and Inspection of Red Cloud, 1874 October 23-27 (Box 51, Folder 6)